using language, reading and writing.
Copernicus' Revolutionary Theory
Nicolaus Copernicus was frightened and his mind was confused.
Although he had tried to ignore them, all his mathematical calculations led to the same conclusion
that the Earth was not the center of the solar system.
Only if you put the sun there did the movements of the other planets in the sky make sense.
Yet he could not tell anyone about his theory as the powerful Christian Church would have punished him
for even suggesting such an idea.
The problem arose because astronomers had noticed that some planets in the sky seemed to stop,
move backward and then go forward in a loop.
Others appeared brighter at times and less bright at others.
Copernicus had thought long and hard about these problems and tried to find an answer.
He had collected observations of the stars and used all his mathematical knowledge to explain them.
But only his new theory could do that.
So between 1510 and 1514 he worked on it,
gradually improving his theory until he felt it was complete.
In 1514 he showed it privately to his friends.
The changes he made to the old theory were revolutionary.
He also suggested that the earth was spinning as it went round the sun
and this explained changes in the movement of the planets and in the brightness of the stars.
His friends were enthusiastic and encouraged him to publish his ideas,
but Copernicus was cautious.
He did not want to be attacked by the Christian Church,
so he only published it as he lay dying in 1543.
Certainly he was right to be careful.
The Christian Church rejected his theory,
saying it was against God's idea and people who supported it would be attacked.
Yet Copernicus' theory is now the basis on which all our ideas of the universe are built.
Copernicus showed this was obviously wrong.
Now people can see that there is a direct link between his theory
and the work of Isaac Newton, Albert Einstein and Stephen Hawking.